This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society and by its software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[music]
For software engineering radio, this is
Robert Blumen. My guest today is Derek
Schaefer. Derek's career has included a
decade long tenure at Microsoft and
roles as CTO and VP at multiple SAS
companies. Derek is the author of the
recent book CLI, a practical guide to
creating modern command line interfaces.
Derek, welcome to Software Engineering
Radio.
Robert, thanks for having me on the
show.
Before we get to talking about modern
command line interfaces, is there
anything you'd like to say about your
background that I didn't cover? Well,
I'm now entering post 30 years. My
career has been a combination of
technical leadership roles and
leadership roles in software, but I've
never really lost my roots as a software
engineer and a data architect. And to be
very honest with your listeners, that's
the thing I always gravitate towards
because it's the funnest part of the
job.
Yeah, I think many listeners to our
podcast feel that way. Now in your book
modern CLIs you tell a history of the
CLI which I found very insightful. I
think a good place to start would be
what is a CLI?
A command line interface is an interface
into a computing environment right that
is predicated on a terminal and
generally a shell and you know the
terminal gives access to the computer.
The shell enables both scripts and
programs. And these programs or these
CLIs are literally built to do discrete
pieces of work inside of an operating
system, whether it be at the operating
system level or with a business
application.
Give a couple of examples.
Sure. If we date ourselves back to the
70s, the classic command line interfaces
of GP, which is a filter for text files,
sort, which is an ordering filter.
You've got cat which is a pipe out into
standard out type command line. Those
are tried andrue age-old command line
interfaces. If we come into the modern
era, there are command lines such as gh
which is the GitHub command line
interface counterpart to its guey. Git.
Obviously the WordPress ecosystem
features the WP CLI which is a modern
command line interface. So you'll find
them in all forms and fashion but they
do have some commonalities at least the
good ones that have survived the test of
time. When I picked up your book, I was
expecting something more like the modern
use cases you gave for CLIs. I always
thought those old school things like GP
were commands. But maybe I'm like that
famous character in literature who was
surprised to learn he had been speaking
pros all his life. Is a command and a
command line interface the same thing?
That's a great question, Robert. And the
short answer is no. You have commands,
right? But the command line interface is
the gateway into the computer if you
would that would invoke those commands.
So historically we went from punch cards
as the interface to invoke functionality
and commands to a terminal which was a
gateway into a shell that enabled access
to scripting environments and commands.
And then obviously in the modern world
we use graphical gateways such as
applications and browser based apps and
mobile apps. I have been in the field
probably about as long as you and I see
commands in a certain way. You have an
interesting history of the CLI. Tell us
that story. Yeah, so I chunked the
history up and purposely in the book did
not want to get into the dredges of
every little incremental innovation in
the terminal and command line history.
But we chunked it up into basically four
or five parts. You know, the first being
the early years where they gained
momentum as we transitioned from punch
cards into an actual teletype interface
that allowed users to type into and view
their output first through a printer and
later on the terminal. We then saw
acceleration in the Unix world as we
began to see both terminal as well as
shell innovations and you know we got
momentum. The real dark era for the
command line was in the 90s when the
popularity of the guey really started to
rise and the question was sincerely
asked do we really need command line
interfaces to a computer can we not do
it all through a graphical user
interface and the short answer to that
was no which led into the Unix era which
was the revival of what had been built
in the Unix era and you know brought
life again to command lines and then we
started into the modern era to where the
innovators who have built modern command
line interfaces have really done some
amazing things. So that was the way we
chose to look at it and wanted to kind
of set some context so that the readers
could understand where this came from
and what were the major catalysts that
caused for the changes that we've seen
today.
Your story is the rise and fall and rise
of command lines. They're back and
bigger than ever before.
They are and they're back at scale. So
if you think about the command line of
the past, you know, the 70s and 80s
version, it was used by power users. It
was used by administrators and it was
used in what I would call high value
environments. You had one administrator,
a few high dollar machines, and it was a
very kind of protected access to a
machine. If you fast forward to today,
every developer has access to shells,
terminals, and they have access to
command line tools such as Git, GH, and
for GitHub, Docker, Kubernetes, each of
the major cloud providers offers a CLI.
These things are really a powering force
in our productivity and workflows today.
And I think that that's really cool.
I have a question in my outline. We've
been talking about this already a little
bit, but I don't think you've told us
exactly what is modern about modern
CLIs.
Yeah. So, there's a couple aspects to
that. I'm going to start with the most
basic, which is what we would call the
command model. And if you go back to the
early days, the Unix philosophy really
stated that these command lines should
do one thing really well and play well
with others. So you saw commands that
were created for a specific purpose. If
I were to come up with a hypothetical
example of like for a CRM application, a
simpleton command line would be CRM add,
right? We would add a customer and it
might take an arguments and we might
have a few switches that would give some
additional functionality. Well, with
that mentality design-wise, you'd also
have to have a CRM delete, a CRM change,
a CRM list, and you can see where the
duplicity in the code and the management
of that becomes a real problem very
quickly. So, in that traditional world,
you saw the command line evolve to have
arguments and then a more organized set
of switches that would allow a single
CLI to do multiple things. So, put that
Robert in a bucket is the traditional
When Lennis Torbolt introduced Git into
the ecosystem, he took some best
practices out of a few different worlds
and introduced what we now refer to as
the object command model. And it is
literally a command and subcommand model
that is usually organized around either
a noun verb or a verb noun. So if I were
to take for example the WP CLI, which is
WordPress's command line interface,
everything is organized around the noun,
a plug-in, a theme, core, and then it's
followed by a subcomand that's a verb.
The reason why this is so innovative is
it allowed very complex command line
interfaces to be built and have the code
isolated almost like we would a micros
service in a SAS environment. and it
allowed reuse of centralized code and
global flags and just really really
robust organization of the application
and that is the preferred model today is
the object command model even though
there's still modern CLIs that are
written traditionally that's what we see
today so that's one aspect of it
if I could think of an example of the
traditional the old Linux admin commands
user ad user mod I forget if there's a
user Dell now if that were written today
would be one command user and there
would be subcommands add remove edit.
Did I get that right? There would so I
would almost organize that traditionally
and say that that user right and then
the argument could be a username or an
ID and we would have switches that would
be like an action equals add delete or
we could have a dash- add a d-delete. If
you were to think about the Unix
operating system or the Linux operating
system holistically, you might have a
general command like we do with with
MySQL to where you're going to have
objects inside of it, which could be
nouns, and then verbs that follow. So,
an object could be a user, add. An
object could be a package, add or
delete. An object could be a networking
protocol, add or delete. And so you can
see how that would allow a single
command line whether it be in a ripple
which is a shell like my SQL or strictly
at the command line to do a lot more
things in a very consistent way. And the
key is we got help out of the man pages
and got them into the command line so
that the user can actually see all of
the options and configurations that are
available to them without having to
bounce in and out of of man pages or
other documentation. So what you're
talking about now the builtin
selfdocumenting
feature of most modern CLIs.
Yes. Yes. And that was significant. It
once again had been introduced in bits
and pieces but tools really popularized
that with git as we brought all of that
into the CLI itself. You mentioned git a
few times and in your book you state
that it was highly innovative in the CLI
space. What were some of the great
innovations that git brought the CLI
world? So first of all, if you think
about scale, the original CIL mantra was
with inside of an operating system and
it might venture its way something such
as arsync to where it's going to
communicate between another machine. But
when you look at Git, we are talking
about local and remote connectivity and
the ability to manage both sides of the
repository equation at scale across
hundreds of millions of users. It really
thought this out in a way that though
people will run into their challenges
with their repo, you don't see the
challenges of repository management of
the past to where code is lost and
documents are, you know, overwritten.
you know, they really got that right at
scale. And I think that that was a very
modern forethought on behalf of the
designers and and the maintainers today
is to make this work at scale.
Something that I think of as the modern
CLI is a command line tool for calling
an API. You call this the API first
architecture. What do you mean by that?
In distributed computing, right, we have
gravitated from using SDK functional
calls locally to calling APIs. So the
modern command line interface finds
itself more organized around making
these remote calls versus calling an
operating system function or versus
calling a function from a local package
that might be compiled into it. though
that's still fair game for the function
of a CLI. We see a lot more remote
communication with APIs in kind of a
more modern sense. And to be honest, any
CLI designer really needs to think about
leveraging once again the Unix
philosophy, do something well and play
well with others. And part of that play
well with others has extended from
standard in, standard out to being able
to make an API call out and receive data
back in as a part of that workstream. if
that makes sense.
I think so. I think that your point is
we're not just pushing text around
through a pipe on the Linux file system,
but we're going out over networks and
consuming worked services in the same
pipelines. Is that where you were going?
That's exactly the point I was trying to
make. Suppose I have a great API that I
set up for my customers or users and
then there's an SDK and now I want to
add a CLI. Should the CLI simply mirror
the API structure or do you think about
it as a different use case?
I hate to give an answer like this, but
it does depend. I would go back to
classic UX mantras of what is the
persona you're trying to serve and what
is the purpose of the CLI. So CLIs can
be used for a number of things.
Traditionally they've been used for
administrative tasks. They've been used
for power users. But I'll give an
example. I'll pick on the WordPress CLI
again. WordPress itself as a PHP and
JavaScript primarily driven user
interface had challenges with longer
running tasks. So things such as
regenerating images on a site was a real
problem. And the WordPress CLI
specifically leverages that
infrastructure with inside of WordPress
core, but they made their own decisions
in terms of performance to be able to
accomplish the task and not be victim of
some of the shortfalls that the
graphical user interface implementation
would have and they crushed it. Right?
That's the de facto way to go regenerate
images on an entire site is through the
CLI because they did it in their way to
solve the need for the persona that they
were servicing.
You just now mentioned longunning tasks.
Something I wanted to ask you about.
What is the model or interaction models
for CLIs to handle longunning tasks?
It depends on what the longunning task
looks like. So first of all when we talk
about interacting with APIs one thing
that is a headwind in any type of of SAS
environments is if you look at your edge
providers or you look at your global
traffic managers or even local traffic
managers they are not in the business of
holding open TCP connections for 5 6 7
10 minutes right it's a real problem
it's a resource problem that they manage
to so if we think about those task of
let's let's take about turning through
data. If we've got a data set to process
that is 100 gig, 500 gig, a terabyte,
and literally has tens of millions of
rows, that long run running task needs
to be mindfully thought out in terms of
how we chunk that up and what are the
system level programming resources that
we leverage. So in that file example, if
I were to look at that and I was sitting
on top of a four core or an 8 core
machine, as a CLI designer, my first
thought is how do I divide that file up
into eight parts and concurrently run a
process on that to leverage that
multi-core machine. The second is how do
I efficiently leverage the memory that I
have locally in a way that I'm not
thrashing on the disk. In the C++ and in
the Go world, the map type, right, which
is kind of a hash bucket element in
memory, has really evolved in recent
years. And Google's patent on what's
called a Swiss table, which allows for
an 8K descriptor on the bucket allows
you to really, really leverage the
memory that's available on local
machines and use that to speed up
process. So, back to your question of
what does a longunning process look like
in a CLI? First of all, you want to
shorten it as much as possible in a
responsible manner. And then to the
extent that it's going to have to
continue to be longer or run over
periods of time that might be subject to
interruptions or failures, you're going
to want to go back to tried and trueue
design tactics such as is having break
points, recovery points, being able to
do retries and not lose that work that
has been in process. So I always go back
to my friend Arsync. I cannot tell you
how many just challenging situations our
sync has has gotten me and and
co-workers of mine out of. And that's a
good one to go look at to say if we're
going to run something for a day, two
days, a week, boy, it sure is nice if
you come back to it and something went
wrong to be able to start where you left
off.
All of what you said certainly very
relevant. Not the question I had in
mind. So let me ask you a different
question which is what about a task
which it doesn't necessarily involve a
staggering amount of data but I kick it
off and it's going to take the provider
2 hours to do. What is a model for that?
First you're going to have to be in a in
a resource environment that will allow
you to do that. So if you are simply
waiting for the provider, let's say that
we put a call out that says I need X to
be done and that could be, you know,
chinning up a bunch of clusters in a
cloud environment. You're going to want
to wait, right, in a responsible way, in
a nonblocking way for that command to
execute. And you're going to want to be
able to make some decisions along the
way as to whether you think that process
is ever going to complete. So in the go
world, this would be a combination of
spinning up a go routine and associating
that with a weight group. And so let's
double down on your question and say
what happens if we asked something to do
a hundred things and needed all of those
to come back. We could have those
assigned to 10 go routines to 10 weight
groups and one by one be able to check
those off as they completed and maintain
a state of waiting until we finish that.
And we'd also mindfully need to make
some decisions if we thought something
was going to error out or not happen to
be able to restart it or retry it.
You mentioned Go just now, which ties
into something else I want to ask you
about. I'm pretty sure the Linux
commands we talked about were all
written in C. You're talking about Go as
another choice. What are the popular
implementation languages in the more
modern space? So you are still seeing
modern CLIs written in C and C++. In the
book we have a spotlight section where
we spotlight a handful of really
largecale popular CLIs and two of them
one represents C which is get and the
other represents C++ which is UCLA speed
test which is a really nifty CLI but
you're also seeing CLI written in PHP,
Python, Node, C. All of those have some
challenges with them because of run
times and the overall plumbing that
surrounds them. But the new kids on the
block of of Go and Rust are gaining
popularity. GitHub is an example that GH
was written not only in Go, but uses a
package called Cobra, which is an object
command framework for Go. And we also
highlight a terminal. It's not a CLI,
but it's a it's a smart terminal called
warp that was written in Rust. In my
view, the more you can leverage system
programming power in a language but not
have to manage the overhead of
multi-threading and memory management
like we had to traditionally with C and
C++. And the lighter weight the runtime
and footprint is, the better of an
application that programming language is
going to be. And I am certainly a fan of
Go from that perspective. give a huge
nod to Rust, but I've also been active
in the WP CLI ecosystem where, you know,
PHP is the language of choice.
Derek, you just now mentioned Go and
some of the tooling that exists to
support building CLIs in Go. Talk about
some of the packages in the Go ecosystem
specifically that help people to build
CLIs. So, Go as you know has a package
ecosystem that supplies functionality
and capabilities beyond what Go's core
is which is is pretty basic. Some of the
more popular ones two written by Steve
Francia just a huge hats off nod to him
is called P flags which is a a flag and
argument package goes standard embedded
package is not that good and it's kind
of commonly known and the second package
that was contributed by Steve was called
Cobra and it uses P flags but it is an
object command model package and he
developed both of those to support Hugo
believe it or not the static command
line driven website editor. So there's
two and those are basics. We cover those
in the book and highly recommend if
you're going to use Go to explore those.
Others that get really interesting as
you look at formatting data, Go does a
good job with its JSON handling and
formatting. But when you get into things
such as terminal graphics, there's a
package called bubble tea which you can
do some really really interesting
dashboardy type things in a command
lines that can be helpful. You will also
see table writer is a popular one that
really gives kind of that granular
control of outputting data into tables
and not having to do a whole lot of
wrestling of standard out in the process
as a developer. And obviously there are
a number of logging packages that are
available as well that make a
developer's job easier. So those are off
the top of my mind. Those would be my
go-tos.
Want to drill down a bit into you can
take these together or in turn Cobra and
P flag. What do they offer to the CLI
developer?
So P flag is the flag package. So go
flag package as I had indicated is not
as strong as it should be. It's got some
challenges with ordering of commands and
other things. And P flags is really a
robust if you wanted to write a
traditional CLI that had arguments and a
number of either short flag, you know, a
dash and an initial or dash and word or
a combination of both arguments to a
command line. It's a really really good
package to use. As we know in an object
command model where we have a command
and subcommand you will also have the
need for flags or switches we could call
them. And so the Cobra package actually
embeds P flags or it uses it as a part
of its implementation and gives you the
best of both of those worlds. So think
once again to our traditional versus
object command model. Just traditional P
flags is good enough for you. If you're
going to go to object commands though
you could write it on your own. I would
highly advise considering Cobra for
writing a CLI in that design pattern.
We've mentioned this tangentially a
couple of times, but to go headon into
this, what is the command object or
object command pattern? As I talked
about earlier, it's where you have a
command subcommand approach to your
command line. And traditionally, you
want to build some consistency into
that. And you will see one of two
patterns. One would be your command
line. So it could be a WP or a GH. And
then the first object or the first
command would either be a noun or a
verb. And then the subcommand would be a
noun or a verb. So in the WordPress
command line interface, WP is the CLI.
Plug-in would be the noun or the first
command. All right, the main command.
And then list for example, which is a
verb would be the subcomand. And that
allows you to meet the administrator or
developer with a level of predictability
and consistency as they maneuver through
an ecosystem that they're familiar with
whether it be cloud computing,
WordPress, Docker, Kubernetes, Git, etc.
I also want to drill down a bit into
bubble te in that it provides a
particular opinionated type of output
format. what are some of the options or
approaches for output formatting
generally in the CLI space?
Yeah, so I'm a traditionalist. I do not
claim to be a bubble tea expert just as
a disclaimer to your listeners. But if I
think about the CLI, there are two major
audiences, right? One is the human user
that would need to see output on the
screen and that could be in a table
format or a plain text format. And then
you have other machines or computers.
Traditionally you will see outputs as
CSV could be JSON. In the case of CLI
like the UCLAS speed test that it feeds
a lot of dashboard and data pipelines.
It it also supports JSON L. And you
could go into any other format that you
saw that a machine would consume. But
that's the way I would kind of divide
the view of traditional outputs from a
CLI. as you get into other human user
use cases. One would be the ripple which
is the read eval print loop. So think of
it like a shell like my SQL. You might
choose to have a little more decorative
and gooey like output in an environment
like that. And that might involve
throwing up some flashing code signals
or other things that bubble tea could or
graphs or progress bars that bubble te
could could help you support. I very
much like the trend toward JSON output.
I'm sure all of us have written some
custom script to parse the output of
particular Unix commands which each one
has highly individual and not anything
like any of the others. Whereas there
are many excellent tools these days for
processing JSON. So if we all agree that
everything's going to be in JSON, then
we can easily write standard tooling to
get exactly what we want out of it. It's
not really a question, but do you have
an opinion about that?
I do. So first of all, huge fan of JSON,
and I do think that any modern CLI
should have JSON as an output option,
not as a default, but as an output
option. I'm going to throw a twist into
the conversation that in the Unix or
Linux world, the expectation has always
been exiting an exit code and that your
data is going to be in the, you know,
standard out or standard error pipes. In
the PowerShell world, that changes.
PowerShell returns an object, a JSON
object and though it sets an exit code,
a administrator has to go look for that.
So if you write a CLI today that does
not support JSON, you are immediately
handicapping yourself in terms of your
interoperability in the PowerShell
world. Now I know your listeners who are
PowerShell experts are going to say ah
that can be you know parsed out and work
can be done but it gets fragile and it
gets fragile quick and you know the
recommendation would be to provide that
option. Back to your early observation
in the original pipeline standard out
world where the CLI did one thing well.
JQ was responsible for that JSON output.
I would argue that that pattern is
probably less powerful today and that
the CLI creator, you know, the developer
and designer should really think through
a good solid JSON strategy for output
because it's just it's expected today.
I'm going to ask you a question about
how GH handles JSON, but let's first
talk about GH, which is GitHub's CLI,
and you feature it in your chapter on
allstar CLI. What was so great about GH?
So the reason why I chose GH or GitHub
CLI for the book is a couple fold but
one is that it sits in a really peculiar
position of being amongst a great. So if
you think about Git and what Git did for
the developer community to come out with
what GitHub did as a commercial
implementation really focused on
developer workflows and how they worked
outside of just code management and to
get that CLI right they could have
chosen to step into Git's world and
duplicated things that Git did did but
they really stuck to that Unix
philosophy of saying let's do one thing
well and respect our demarc point and
play well with others. And so it brought
par from the GitHub web enabled world to
meet the developer where many developers
operate which is inside of a shell. And
so the modernness there is more from a
design pattern how they chose to handle
that. The second modern nature to that
is is just you know how complex the
GitHub world is at scale. We're not
talking hundreds or thousands or
hundreds of thousands of users. You're
talking millions distributed across the
globe. And they really had to get that
right. And in my opinion, they did.
I use GitHub and I use GH. Sometimes I
still use the web for something that I
could do with GH. Does that mean they
failed or there are just different use
cases for different situations?
I think it's a great question. So first
I think that a good CLI right is going
to reduce cognitive load on a user and
be really easy to understand. And one
could argue that in both of those worlds
there is a bit of mastery that needs to
take place with both Git and GitHub.
We've all had to go out to Stack
Overflow or look up and in and help how
to do something in particular that was
perplexing us. And I'll admit I've done
the same as you, Robert, and gone to the
web version to say I'm just gonna go
take care of this problem in a way that
I can. So I don't think that they've
failed, but I do think that there is
some cognitive headwind that they have
presented the user in their
implementation. And could that be
improved upon? Sure.
We're all using more and more of these
large language model command-based
interfaces and we want them to do more
things for us. So they are developing
interfaces with tools. There are a
couple of different approaches. One is
get it to use your CLI. The other is you
go through a MCP server to a custom API.
And we covered this in an earlier
episode where it was discussed that the
API for the MCP server is actually going
to look a lot different than the
traditional API. Do you have a either a
preference or uh just observation about
should AIs be using the CLIs or are we
going to end up writing custom APIs to
reach the same back end?
Great question, Robert. I think it's
going to be a balance of both. But at
the heart of things, what is interesting
about artificial intelligence is it is
literally and I'll take which we
highlight in the book the way that warp
terminal goes about looking at a CLI and
what's capable. We've never thought
about a CLI being crawled, right? We
thought about a user invoking help. We
thought about a user taking advantage of
autocomplete, but we never envisioned
those as being assets that would be
consumed by an LLM and be leveraged for
implementation. And that's part of one
of the considerations that I have a call
to action in the end of the book is to
really think out how that documentation
and how you're documenting your CLI
because they are going to be discovered
and to the extent that you provide
machine ready documentation you'll be
more successful. Now should that be the
de facto going through a CLI versus an
MCP? Boy, I tell you, if I had the
answer to that, I'd probably have a
different set of tasks on my plate at
work tomorrow. I think it's going to be
a balance. I will tell you where we over
complicate things in the industry
historically. And if we go proprietary
or go down a route that isn't accessible
to all, you'll see winners and losers.
And for those tools that follow the
simpleton approach of the Unix
philosophy, right, being able to operate
off of standard text files and being
able to work well with others, I think
you'll see more longevity. So, if I had
to put my bet on something, the CLI is
probably going to outlive certain MCP
implementations. I'm not saying it's
going to outlive the MCP, but I think
you'll see less friction in environments
that go directly with the CLI for
certain use cases. Part of what you said
I wasn't expecting. So to make sure I
understood this, when you're talking
about a CLI being crawled, do you mean I
could tell an LLM, I have this tool in
my shell. It's called GH, go figure out
what it does and then the LLM will start
running. Okay, GH help, GH commands.
List the commands, the commands add.
Okay, GH add help. and it can discover
the entire surface area of the tool by
reading the embedded self-documentation
and train itself up without you having
provided any kind of uh custom adapter.
Is that where you're going with that?
That's where I'm going with that. And if
you think about as a CLI designer or
developer, we might give reasonable help
knowing that, you know, system admins
and stuff, they're smart people. They're
going to figure it out. and we might
give an example. Well, now the trend in
a more modern CLI would be to give a
little more detailed help and give a ton
of examples because those examples will
be consumed by not just your human
users, but they're going to be consumed
by LLMs. And you're seeing that like
warp is a terminal today. That's part of
of how they're discovering CLI
implementations. With a command like
git, I often ask Claude or chat GPT, how
do I do a particular thing in Git? I
believe because Git is so popular that
there's an enormous amount of Git
knowledge in the AI's training data. It
doesn't even need to discover how Git
works. It knows.
That would be the second element of
this. If you have an open-sourced driven
project, right, where that source code
is available on Bitbucket, GitHub,
whatever it may be, then if it's popular
and has, you know, to use a Wikipedia
term, if it's notable, it's highly
likely that an LLM will have crawled it
and understood it. So, for example, we
know for a fact that the majors have
been trained in the WPCLI just because
it's been in existence since 2011. It's
PHP, it's open source, it's there. I
think where this gets interesting is if
you are a company that might have a
non-opensource CLI or a proprietary CLI
but your user base might be using AI
enabled tools including cloud code
including warp as a smart intelligent
terminal. Are you doing everything you
can to make yourself accessible and
understandable to the LLM? And hence we
enter this brave new world which is
actually one of the chapters I have in
the book that we start to to not give
the answers to this but ponder what the
future looks like.
To change direction a bit I wanted to
cover authentication
and maybe authorization
which every API has to handle that and
therefore the CLI which accesses it must
also handle that. How do CLIs do
authentication?
This is a really critical area of
discussion and thanks for asking the
question, Robert. If you think about in
a small captive world, it was okay to go
ahead and put in a command that might
have included a password and a username,
but from a security perspective, that
ends up in history, and that's not a
good thing. You would also find
configuration files in YAML, or you'd
find those in JSON. You might find
exported environmental variables that
would have these. And once again, I'll
do something to try to at least
centralize this. And I really can't
honestly use the word protect, but maybe
I'll use the word to try to be
responsible with this, but it's a
challenge, right? Because a good hacker,
they know exactly what they're looking
for if they get into a system. Another
approach, which is a horrible approach,
would be to compile those credentials
into the binary, and it takes a a good
black hat, you know, a matter of
minutes, if if not, you know, a half an
hour to unpack that. So we really get
back to the semantics of some of the
things we're doing in the SAS
environment in terms of how are we using
keybased approaches, how are we storing
credentials and credential repositories.
And back to that Unix philosophy of
doing one thing and one thing well. Your
CLI should not be raising its hand
saying I am a credential manager. I'm
going to do that well. There are other
software systems that are better suited
for that. And again in in the Unix
philosophy to play nicely with others, a
CLI should play nicely with these
credentiing systems because they're your
best ally in this world that we live in.
You might not be a big fan then of a CLI
I use a lot, the AWS CLI, because you
have to log in and it gives you short
duration access tokens.
It's not that I'm not a fan and logging
in. There's a couple of headwinds that a
CLI can create, right? And cloud code's
a good example one, but we'll also talk
about AWS. Whenever you're forcing the
user to do something that is outside
what they ask the CLI to do, so a login
is a a cognitive load. It's a headwind.
It does have impact. But in AWS's world,
I understand and respect why they take
that approach. and the CLI is being
used, right, to interact with workflows
and and get work done and that short
duration is just part of the world at
scale that they live with. Could they
have a better implementation? Probably,
but I'm I'm not going to go online to
criticize it. You know, this is one of
the challenges that we face with CLIs.
I happen to know how this works with
AWS. It stores the credentials in a
directory. So what's interesting about
that now is that the CLI is stateful
whereas I think of them from the
beginning as being stateless
are stateful CLIs an actual thing.
So state management is an interesting
question. If you think about CLI such as
my SQL they will rely on state to get
their job done or even some of the
content management CLI will rely on
state in a database. I would argue that
a CLI that is dependent on state, it
might have to have it due to the system
it interoperates with, but if it's for
something such as a credential or some
general, you know, configuration
parameters, that's probably not the best
thing. I do get into state in the book
where we talk about the need for state
and one example I give is if you think
about doing network work in the internet
of things and have a small CLI that
might be collecting data. It's fair game
in C C++ or Go or another language to
use an embedded database to collect that
state process it. But you don't want
that to be the system of record. you
want to ship that off as soon as
possible to a true system of record. So
Robert, I would I would come back to
your question and say are we looking at
things like we would in the SAS software
world of saying what is the system of
record for that state and is the CLI the
best place for that to be managed and
stored and in some cases the answer
might be yes but probably in most cases
it's going to be a design flaw. I think
about another command like curl and if
I'm hitting an API, I need to usually
pass in an O token as a curl header or
as a HTTP header. What the AWS CLI
enables me to do is I can log in and now
I can work for two hours without having
to think about credentials because the
credentials are a form of state. So
maybe the question is do you take a
stand on per use or stored credentials?
So it really [clears throat] depends on
what the workload is in the AWS
environment. You're in there, right, to
do work. And I think that that is the
overall premise of allowing a user to
get work done before they exit is a good
thing to where in curl you're in and out
of that transaction whether you're
downloading a web page, you're actually
hitting an API because curl can do a lot
of things. It's more transactional in
nature. I think it does present a
problem and I come back to SSH. The way
that SSH solved this problem is through
public and private keys and I think we
are going to continue to want to sharpen
the pencil in terms of of how we look at
authentication in state management and
CLI. There's no one answer.
There's one last topic want to hit
before we start to wrap up. I don't know
if it's a CLI feature or a shell
feature. How does completion work and
should your CLI provide it?
So autocomp completion is literally a
file that you would supply with a CLI
that would allow the shell environment,
right, to be able to read that and
autocomplete. And I believe that you
should for two reasons. one, it's
helpful to the end user, but second,
back to this LLM world to where the more
data we provide to external entities
such as an LLM, the better you're going
to play well in this new world that
we're entering into. It's another reason
why I like packages like Cobra that
Cobra makes that autocomp completion,
you know, it bakes it in as a package or
as a command to your CLI so that you can
run it, create those text files with the
autocomplete and and you're off to the
races. So, it really reduces the
workload on a developer to have to
implement that.
We may have talked about this already,
but do you have any thoughts that you
haven't already expressed on where are
CLI's headed? We've talked about in the
LLM driven world, I think that there is
going to be a requirement of CLIs to
handle non-deterministic returns in
addition to their the current world,
which is generally deterministic. And
we're already starting to see those
challenges surface in cloud code, for
example. But any CLI that is hitting an
LLM and processing structured output,
the answer is not going to be the same
for every call. And you're going to have
to think through that from a design
perspective. I also think that if we
look at the premise of a CLI to go do
something, right? The what and the
developer builds in how we do that in a
regulatory compliant world. So thinking
healthcare, thinking banking, thinking a
number of worlds, even just with a
general sock audit, you also are going
to have to be able to capture in the CLI
who did it, when they did it, and more
importantly, who authorized it. So now
we're getting into workflows. And those
logs might not be punched out into
standard error and into your general
logging format. Those logs might require
the CLI designer to provide options out
to Splunk or Logly or Data Dog or other
places where you can punch an
asynchronous JSON payload to actually
capture that data. So again, more
complications the more complicated our
world becomes. And I think that that is
why CLI designers really need to to do
upfront design work to capture
everything that they need to be thinking
about in their CLI. The last response I
would have to that question is if you
think about the power that PowerShell
has brought to the computing
environments. There's an argument that
says you can probably get away with 80%
of what you need to do by just writing
PowerShell scripts. And that scares me
Robert a little bit. I champion
PowerShell. I champion the people who
have gotten good at it. But I do think
there is a still a clean demarcation
point between control and workflow which
is in the shell environments and the
work to be done and the testing and
rigor that needs to go into an actual
compiled or let's call it versions in
the PHP or Python world application such
as a CLI.
Derek, as we wrap up, where can
listeners find your book?
Easiest place to get there is on the web
at moderncli.dev
dev and there are links out to Amazon,
Barnes & Noble and and other providers.
It is only available in paperback and
hard coverver, but we made pricing super
low because I wanted to make it
accessible. Robert, one of the design
tenants for the book and one of the
reasons why we selected Go for the
examples. It's not about Go, but Go. The
examples are in go is I truly wanted
whether you could be a high school
student or a junior college student and
especially if you got a limited budget.
I wanted people to be able to have
accessibility to the book and
accessibility to the resources they
would need to do the exercises in the
book either for free or in a very
reasonable price point. And I was really
adamant about that as we did this. Are
there any other locations on the web
relating to you or your properties you'd
like to point listeners to?
Definitely LinkedIn account Derek
Schaefer to connect up there on GitHub.
I've actually got a couple of plugins in
the WordPress space that have actually
been approved and will be coming out and
I'm on Twitter, but LinkedIn would be
probably the primary place to find me.
And my passion and desire to write this
book was to capture the history, the
evolution of the CLI and to help people
think about how they design them and
write the best possible software product
that they can for whatever their use
case is, whether it be individually or
personally or they're doing something
major for their employer in a computing
environment. And I wish people the best
of the luck and and congratulate them if
they get the opportunity to work on the
CLI project because they're quite fun.
Derek, I must say it's been a pleasure
speaking to you about modern CLIs and
thank you for speaking to Software
Engineering Radio.
Robert, thanks for having me.
For Software Engineering Radio, this has
been Robert Blumen. Thank you for
listening. [music]
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, [music]
or through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamse-radio.net.
[music] This and all other episodes of
SE Radio is licensed under Creative
Common License 2.5. Thanks for
listening.